A Guide to the Letters received and sent from the Virginia Land Office, 1774-1977
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Letters received and sent from the Virginia Land Office, 1774-1977
The Library of Virginia
LOI 18
25.5 cu. ft. (73 boxes)
Virginia. Land Office
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession LOI 18 transferred by the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1948.
Biographical Information
The act which established the previous Land Office passed the General Assembly on 22 June 1779. The register was the head of the Office and was appointed by joint ballot of both houses of the legislature.
Scope and Content
These records contain incoming correspondence to the register of the Land Office, including the period the secretary of the commonwealth held the office, dealing primarily with business affairs. Included are requests for warrants and copies of grants and surveys, letters which accompanied incoming surveys, letters seeking information about military bounty lands, and inquiries regarding the manner of resolving conflicts pertaining to land possession. Many entries from the 20th century involve requests for information for genealogical or historical research, frequently to establish eligibility for membership in the Daughters of the American Revolution.
The General Assembly of 1867 appointed the register to be superintendent of weights and measures and that of 1874 added to his duties those of the superintendent of public buildings. The correspondence directed to the former office was filed separately and is described in entry 126, but that of the latter is incorporated in the regular land Office correspondence. The little extant correspondence directed to the register in his capacity as ex officio secretary of the Board of Immigration, an office assigned him by legislative action of March 1875, is described in entry 137.
Although some of the 19th century letters have notes for replies annexed (particularly during the periods 1810-1814 and 1875-1899), it is not until the 20th century that copies of the replies are attached to most letters received, sometimes typed onto the back of the original letter received. In 1948, the Land Office records were transferred from the custody of the Secretary of the Commonwealth to the State Library, and in 1952 the duties of the Register of the Land Office were transferred from the Secretary of the Commonwealth to the state librarian. Following the transfer, correspondence regarding the Land Office records was conducted by the state librarian, Randolph W. Church from 1948 to 1972, and Donald Haynes from 1972.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Virginia. Land Office; Virginia. Secretary of the Commonwealth
Subjects:
Bounties, Military -- Virginia.; Right of property -- Virginia.
Genre and Form Terms:
Correspondence.; State government records -- Virginia
Contents List
- Letters received and sent from the Virginia Land Office, 1774-1977., Extent: 73. (Box 1-73)
  Chronological
  - Letters received, 1774-May 1798., 12 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters received, June 1798-December 1802., 10 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters received, January 1803-December 1806., 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Letters received, 1807-December 1813., 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Letters received, January 1814-June 1817., 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Letters received, July 1817-June 1820., 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Letters received, July 1820-December 1823., 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Letters received, January 1824-December 1826., 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Letters received, January 1827-April 1830., 7 folders (Box 9)
  - Letters received, May 1830-August 1831., 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Letters received, 1831-March 1833., 9 folders (Box 11)
  - Letters received, April 1833-May 1834., 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Letters received, August 1834-August 1835., 7 folders (Box 13)
  - Letters received, September 1835-December 1836., 7 folders (Box 14)
  - Letters received, January 1837-April 1838., 7 folders (Box 15)
  - Letters received, May 1838-May 1839., 5 folders (Box 16)
  - Letters received, June 1839-April 1840., 7 folders (Box 17)
  - Letters received, May 1840-September 1840., 5 folders (Box 18)
  - Letters received, October 1840-May 1841., 5 folders (Box 19)
  - Letters received, June 1841-March 1842., 6 folders (Box 20)
  - Letters received, April 1842-October 1842., 5 folders (Box 21)
  - Letters received, November 1842-August 1843., 6 folders (Box 22)
  - Letters received, September 1843-May 1844., 6 folders (Box 23)
  - Letters received, June 1844-January 1845., 6 folders (Box 24)
  - Letters received, February 1845-August 1845., 6 folders (Box 25)
  - Letters received, September 1845-February 1846., 5 folders (Box 26)
  - Letters received, March 1846-June 1846., 4 folders (Box 27)
  - Letters received, July 1846-November 1846., 6 folders (Box 28)
  - Letters received, December 1846-May 1847., 6 folders (Box 29)
  - Letters received, June 1847-September 1847., 4 folders (Box 30)
  - Letters received, October 1847-April 1848., 5 folders (Box 31)
  - Letters received, May 1848-August 1848., 4 folders (Box 32)
  - Letters received, September 1848-February 1849., 6 folders (Box 33)
  - Letters received, March 1849-August 1849., 5 folders (Box 34)
  - Letters received, September 1849-January 1850., 5 folders (Box 35)
  - Letters received, February 1850-May 1850., 5 folders (Box 36)
  - Letters received, June 1850-September 1850., 5 folders (Box 37)
  - Letters received, October 1850-March 1851., 6 folders (Box 38)
  - Letters received, April 1851-July 1851., 4 folders (Box 39)
  - Letters received, August 1851-November 1851., 5 folders (Box 40)
  - Letters received, December 1851-June 1852., 7 folders (Box 41)
  - Letters received, July 1852-January 1853., 7 folders (Box 42)
  - Letters received, February 1853-July 1853., 6 folders (Box 43)
  - Letters received, August 1853-16 January 1854., 6 folders (Box 44)
  - Letters received, 17 January 1854-16 April 1855., 5 folders (Box 45)
  - Letters received, 17 April 1854-15 July 1854., 6 folders (Box 46)
  - Letters received, 16 July 1854-October 1854., 7 folders (Box 47)
  - Letters received, November 1854-February 1855., 6 folders (Box 48)
  - Letters received, March 1855-15 June 1855., 5 folders (Box 49)
  - Letters received, 16 June 1855-September 1855., 7 folders (Box 50)
  - Letters received, October 1855-March 1856., 8 folders (Box 51)
  - Letters received, April 1856-September 1856., 6 folders (Box 52)
  - Letters received, October 1856-March 1857., 7 folders (Box 53)
  - Letters received, April 1857-July 1857., 8 folders (Box 54)
  - Letters received, August 1857-November 1857., 7 folders (Box 55)
  - Letters received, December 1857-April 1858., 6 folders (Box 56)
  - Letters received, May 1858-September 1858., 5 folders (Box 57)
  - Letters received, October 1858-March 1859., 6 folders (Box 58)
  - Letters received, April 1859-September 1859., 6 folders (Box 59)
  - Letters received, October 1859-December 1860., 7 folders (Box 60)
  - Letters received, January 1861-June 1870., 11 folders (Box 61)
  - Letters received, July 1870-December 1871., 8 folders (Box 62)
  - Letters received, January 1872-June 1873., 7 folders (Box 63)
  - Letters received, July 1873-August 1874., 7 folders (Box 64)
  - Letters received, August 1874-June 1876., 8 folders (Box 65)
  - Letters received, July 1876-September 1878., 9 folders (Box 66)
  - Letters received, October 1878-February 1895., 8 folders (Box 67)
  - Letters received, March 1895-1911., 14 folders (Box 68)
  - Letters received, 1912-December 1922., 19 folders (Box 69)
  - Letters received, January 1923-September 1923., 9 folders (Box 70)
  - Letters received, October 1923-June 1924., 9 folders (Box 71)
  - Letters received, 1927-Undated, S-Z., 10 folders (Box 72)
  - Letters Received and Sent, 1948-1977., 57 folders (Box 73)
    Alphabetical
    - General Folder A, 1951-1964. (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - F. W. Alley, 1950. (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - Mason Alvis, 1951-1952. (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - J. W. Baldwin, 1948-1953. (Box 73, Folder 4)
    - W. W. Baldwin and C. B. Belcher, 1951-1962. (Box 73, Folder 5)
    - C. W. Belcher, 1950. (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - Hubert C. Bickers, 1950. (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - R. C. Brown, 1948. (Box 73, Folder 8)
    - Fred Burgess, 1951. (Box 73, Folder 9)
    - General Folder C, 1950-1960. (Box 73, Folder 10)
    - Charles Carroll Carter, 1951-1953. (Box 73, Folder 11)
    - Loncey Clevinger, 1951-1953. (Box 73, Folder 12)
    - W. W. Coleman, 1951-1952. (Box 73, Folder 13)
    - General Folder D, 1958-1964. (Box 73, Folder 14)
    - Tucker R. Dearing, 1952. (Box 73, Folder 15)
    - Ray A. Dillon, 1951-1953. (Box 73, Folder 16)
    - L. N. Donati, 1949. (Box 73, Folder 17)
    - General Folder E, 1950. (Box 73, Folder 18)
    - H. D. Eichelberger, 1951. (Box 73, Folder 19)
    - Anderson Elswick, 1950-1952. (Box 73, Folder 20)
    - R. F. Filer and Mildred O. Filer, 1949-1954. (Box 73, Folder 21)
    - James E. Foltz and Mary J. Foltz, 1949-1950. (Box 73, Folder 22)
    - George A. Ford, 1950-1951. (Box 73, Folder 23)
    - H. M. Ford, Jr., 1953-1954. (Box 73, Folder 24)
    - Beamon T. Forrest, 1948. (Box 73, Folder 25)
    - General Folder G, 1975. (Box 73, Folder 26)
    - C. C. Gouldman, 1948-1949. (Box 73, Folder 27)
    - John C. Gouldman, 1949-1950. (Box 73, Folder 28)
    - Wallace E. Graves, 1949-1950. (Box 73, Folder 29)
    - David A. Harrison, III, 1977. (Box 73, Folder 30)
    - General Folder H, 1969. (Box 73, Folder 31)
    - Frank Hatter, 1951-1952. (Box 73, Folder 32)
    - William E. Hogg, 1952. (Box 73, Folder 33)
    - Morton H. Hopkins, 1951-1952. (Box 73, Folder 34)
    - J. W. Hutchens, 1958. (Box 73, Folder 35)
    - L. C. Jones, 1950-1951. (Box 73, Folder 36)
    - Mrs. Mary E. Jones, 1949. (Box 73, Folder 37)
    - General Folder K, 1954. (Box 73, Folder 38)
    - T. C. Keith, 1952-1953. (Box 73, Folder 39)
    - W. W. Koontz 1950-1951. (Box 73, Folder 40)
    - General Folder L, 1949-1957. (Box 73, Folder 41)
    - General Folder M, 1950-1966. (Box 73, Folder 42)
    - Charlie Matney, 1951. (Box 73, Folder 43)
    - James R. May 1948-1949. (Box 73, Folder 44)
    - C. S. Minter 1949-1951. (Box 73, Folder 45)
    - Bethel Mitchell, 1957. (Box 73, Folder 46)
    - General Folder P 1949-1962. (Box 73, Folder 47)
    - Robert S. Peters, 1967. (Box 73, Folder 48)
    - J. F. Quisenberry, 1949. (Box 73, Folder 49)
    - Nettie Hunt Russell, 1949. (Box 73, Folder 50)
    - General Folder S 1950-1972. (Box 73, Folder 51)
    - Lewis S. Sachs, 1950. (Box 73, Folder 52)
    - Allen Stuart, 1949-1950. (Box 73, Folder 53)
    - Clyde W. Tabor, 1951-1952. (Box 73, Folder 54)
    - R. Vernon Taylor, 1948-1950. (Box 73, Folder 55)
    - B. L. Tremelon, 1950. (Box 73, Folder 56)
    - General Folder W, 1956-1973. (Box 73, Folder 57)